If you were to take a look at your teeth underneath a microscope, the enamel of your tooth, even though it's the hardest substance in our bodies, it's still pretty porous.
And what happens is that those porous areas are the ones that we are utilizing to whiten our teeth.
So here's what happens.
You have a very porous tooth structure and onto that tooth structure you put one of the whitening agents on there.
Usually the whitening agents are made of a hydrogen peroxide or a carbamide peroxide.
It's not really truly bleach as some people are led to believe.
So it's a hydrogen peroxide, and when you put that up against the structure of the enamel, all of those porous areas, from those areas you're pulling and drawing stain out from the tooth.
And so during that time that you are sitting with that whitening agent on teeth, you are actually pulling and drawing stain out.
The longer period of time you're sitting with that whitener up against the tooth, the more whitening that is existing during that time.
Also of course we need to consider the strength of the tooth whitener.
Many of the tooth whiteners that you're purchasing in stores, the grocery stores and the supermarkets and department stores have a lower concentration of that peroxide.
So it may take you longer to get to your results and you'll have to be a little bit more patient versus the in-office or in professional store whitening where you have a higher concentration of that peroxide.
So you're getting much more whitening in a shorter period of time.